A Guide to the Iris Alina Ruiz Williams Papers, 1939-1965: SC 0223
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Iris Alina Ruiz Williams Papers,
1939-1965
Special Collections, James Madison University
Williams, Iris Alina Ruiz, 1921-2010
SC 0223
1.32 cubic feet; 2 boxes, 1 rolled storage container
The Iris Alina Ruiz Williams Papers, 1939-1965, comprise photographs, drawings, a scrapbook, and a fencing foil from Williams' time as a student at Madison College and as an alumna.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated in November 2012 by Alice Williams Krum, Iris Alina Ruiz Williams' daughter. Krum made a second donation in July 2017.
Bio/Historical Note
Iris Alina Ruiz Williams (1921-2010), nicknamed "Titi," was born in Aguadilla, Puerto Rico. At age 17, she arrived in the United States for the very first time to attend Madison College where she studied Elementary Education. During her time at Madison College, from 1939-1942, Iris was an active member in various organizations. She served as treasurer for the Spanish Club, and typist for The Breeze and The Schoolma'am yearbook. She was a member of the Y.W.C.A, Newman Club, Lee Literary Society, and was a lifetime member of Theta Sigma Epsilon.
Upon graduating from Madison College in 1942, Iris married Harry Edward Williams Jr. whom she met at Madison College. They had four children. Iris later became a successful elementary school teacher and adult education teacher. She was also actively involved in her church and several organizations in her community throughout her life.
Scope and Content
The Iris Alina Ruiz Williams Papers, 1939-1965, comprise photographs, drawings, a scrapbook, and a fencing foil from Williams' time as a student at Madison College and as an alumna.
The photographs are foldered according the following categories: classmate portraits, Madison College campus/events, and non-campus subject matter. Photographs that do not clearly document the Madison College campus or college-sponsored events are filed with non-campus photographs. Madison College related photographs include Wilson Hall, commencement ceremonies, May Day celebrations, hiking, snow scenes, dorm rooms, and candid photographs featuring Williams and her classmates. Photographs documenting non-campus scenes/events depict the New York World's Fair (1939), the Memorial Amphitheater at Arlington National Cemetery, and beach scenes.
A series of eight drawings, sketched by Williams for a college art class, depict various campus scenes.
A biographical sketch of Williams, written after her death in 2010, is included along with a photocopy of a ship's manifest documenting Williams' departure from San Juan, Puerto Rico in June 1939 for New York, with Madison College being her ultimate destination. She is listed under her maiden name, Iris Ruiz, on the document.
Williams' scrapbook documents alumnae news and activities and includes newspaper clippings, programs, and ephemera.
Williams' fencing foil used in her college fencing class is included.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Separated Material
Two student handbooks and a souvenir book of Harrisonburg were removed from the collection and cataloged.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Madison College -- History; Madison College -- Alumni and alumnae; Madison College -- Students; Madison College -- Students -- Social life and customs; James Madison University -- Students -- History; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- Description and travel; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- History
Genre and Form Terms:
Photographs; Scrapbooks; Pencil drawings
- Non-Madison College photographs, 1939-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Madison College campus/event photographs (folder 1 of 5), 1939-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Madison College campus/event photographs (folder 2 of 5), 1939-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Madison College campus/event photographs (folder 3 of 5), 1939-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Madison College campus/event photographs (folder 4 of 5), 1939-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Madison College campus/event photographs (folder 5 of 5), 1939-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Classmate portrait photographs, 1939-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Madison College sign (pencil on paper), ca. 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Henrietta doll (pencil on paper), ca. 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Wilson Hall (pencil on paper), ca. 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Dorm room interior (pencil on paper), ca. 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Madison College buildings (pencil on paper), ca. 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Wilson Hall cupola (pencil on paper), ca. 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Madison College building entrance (pencil on paper), ca. 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Madison College smoke stack (pencil on paper), ca. 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- USS Coamo manifest (photocopy) and biographical sketch, 1939, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Madison College Alumnae Scrapbook, 1943-1965 (Box OV 1)
- Fencing Foil, undated (Rolledstorage 1)